Registering Web Services in the BioCatalogue

The Problem: “My Web Services are not visible…”

So…

Anyone can easily register Web Services in the BioCatalogue

These service are instantly available to the community, tool developers and search engines

Service providers can advertise, describe and monitor their services through the BioCatalogue

Any registered users (members) can submit any Web Service to the BioCatalogue. You do not have to be the provider of the service to submit it to the BioCatalogue. Click here to become a Member of the BioCatalogue.

Currently the BioCatalogue support SOAP, REST and Soaplab services.

Submitting SOAP service to the BioCatalogue

Given that most existing SOAP services have a WSDL document, registering a SOAP service entry into the BioCatalogue requires only the WSDL url. The BioCatalogue WSDL parser automatically structures the data from the WSDL file. To submit a SOAP service with a defined WSDL file:

Select 'SOAP' from the 'Register a Service' page in the BioCatalogue

Paste your WSDL url in the form and click preview

Provide additional description to the service. This is optional but very useful. You may add these descriptions after you submit the service

Click 'Submit' to submit your service

Once the service is successfully submitted you can add more annotation (descriptions, tags, example values) to the service and its operations, inputs or outputs.

Submitting REST service to the BioCatalogue

To submit a REST service all you need is the REST endpoint and the service name.

Select 'REST' from the 'Register a Service' page in the BioCatalogue

Paste the base URL of the REST service

Provide a name for the service

Provide additional description for the service. This is optional but very useful. You may add these descriptions after you submit the service

Click 'Submit' to submit your service

Once the service is successfully submitted you can add more annotation (descriptions, tags, example values) to the service. You will also be able to add the different REST endpoints which make up the service.

Adding REST Endpoints

Below is an example on how to add these endpoints to a REST service; this example is based on the BioCatalogue's own REST API. Click on the 'Add New Endpoints' button, which is found under the 'REST Endpoints' tab. This should bring up a pop-up with some help text and a text box to enter the endpoints.

A REST endpoint takes in parameters, some of which are mandatory, some optional. The endpoints I will register are:

http://www.biocatalogue.org/search?q={query}

http://www.biocatalogue.org/services/{id}

http://www.biocatalogue.org/tags/{tagname}?namespace={namespace}

Provided the base URL does not contain a question mark ”?”, endpoints can be expressed as paths relative to the base URL:

/search?q={query}

/services/{id}

/tags/{tagname}?namespace={the-namespace-of-the-tags}

Placing curly braces around a parameter tells the BioCatalogue that the parameter is mandatory. In the above endpoints, q, id, tagname, and namespace are mandatory parameters. All other parameters without curly braces will be treated as part of the endpoint and not a parameter.

After submitting the above entries, the BioCatalogue will register the following endpoints and associate them with the registered service:

GET /search?q={query}

GET /services/{id}

GET /tags/{tagname}?namespace={the-namespace-of-the-tags}

Notice the HTTP GET at the the beginning of the registered endpoint; If you do not provide an HTTP method for an endpoint, the BioCatalogue assumes the default: GET. To register endpoints that use other HTTP methods, simply put the HTTP method, followed by a space, then the endpoint. The supported methods are GET, PUT, POST, and DELETE. For example:

GET /{resource}/{id} is the same as /{resource}/{id}

POST /{resource}

PUT /{resource}/{id}

DELETE /{resource}/{id}?verbose={true_or_false}

The base URL of a REST service can also contain query parameters, but these query parameters are not configurable. Using the DDBJ services as an example, the base URL would have to be registered as ”http://xml.nig.ac.jp/rest/Invoke?service=DDBJ”.

With such a base URL, you cannot enter endpoints with a relative path, they must have the full URL:

http://xml.nig.ac.jp/rest/Invoke?service=DDBJ&method=countBasePair&accession={accession}

http://xml.nig.ac.jp/rest/Invoke?service=DDBJ&method=getAllFeatures&accession={accession}

http://xml.nig.ac.jp/rest/Invoke?service=DDBJ&method=getFFEntry&accession={accession}

The above endpoint will result in the following BioCatalogue entries:

GET /?method=countBasePair

GET /?method=getAllFeatures

GET /?method=getFFEntry

The ”/?” in the registered endpoint is just a way of saying that the base URL for that service contains a query parameter; it can be renamed to ”?”, ”/&”, ”&”, or anything that makes sense to you.

Submitting Soaplab service to the BioCatalogue

Soaplab service are command line application wrapped as Web Services.

To submit a soaplab 1 service:

From the soaplab server which may look like <base URL/axis/services> look for 'AnalysisFactory' and copy the corresponding WSDL

Select 'Soaplab Server' from the 'Register a Service' page in the BioCatalogue

Paste the WSDL URL you have copied in the form and click preview

Click 'Submit' to submit your service

To submit a soaplab 2 service:

From the soaplab server copy the WSDL ending with <services/list?wsdl>

Select 'Soaplab Server' from the 'Register a Service' page in the BioCatalogue

Paste the WSDL URL you have copied in the form and click preview

Click 'Submit' to submit your service

Note that it may take a little while for all services to be registered.
Once the service is successfully submitted you can add more annotation (descriptions, tags, example values) to the service and its operations, inputs or outputs.

Attending

EBI - Eric, Hamish, Thomas, Rodrigo

Manchester - Carole, Jiten, Katy Apologies

Franck(away on caBIG conference)

Minuting

Eric

Agenda

Actions from Previous Meeting

Action All → Read the paper on biocatalogue sent to the mailing list by Carole

Action Carole → Speak to Steve, of the Manchester EMBRACE team about biocatalogue

Action Eric → post database model to mailing list for comments

Action All → Planning on prototype/to building a community/to building a highly scalable infrastructure

Action All → Read on building highly scalable web applications (links to sent to list by Jits)

Action Eric/Jits/Thomas → Design to with possible replacement of components in mind

Action All : Need flyer for ISMB meeting

 

Round-table

Upcoming Meetings

Carole, Katy, Jits, Thomas, Hamish & Rodrigo going to ISMB meeting (20-23 July)

Carole and Katy doing paper for the project kick-off meeting for our sysmo-db project Any Other Business (AOB)

Shall we set up a developper blog at this stage of the project to interact with potential users?

Can Manchester team access EBI ticket tracker?

From Robert: can you make sure these two items are discussed at the BioCatalogue meeting:

1. Attempt to draw up a “how to approach annotating a service” – a best practise document as a guide to people “out there” who want to attempt such an action. this is a start for something we need for our Briefings in Bioinformatics paper

    2. Scheduling time for Franck to do some work on ONDEx workflows in the near future....

Minutes

On actions from previous meeting

 1. Carole to resend paper to mailing list for reading and/or comments
 2. Carole Spoke to Steve of the Manchester EMBRACE team. They want to implement some quick fix solution to catalogue EMBRACE services. They intend to use BioCatalogue in the future
 3.  Eric put a db schema on the wiki. To repost to mailing list for comments
 4. Agreement not to worry about the db model being rails driven for the prototype. However, the constraints introduced by rails should be clearly documented with possible solutions should migration to another backend model be necessary after the prototype. Jiten suggested that Passenger and Ruby Enterprise Edition be explored for the BioCatalogue prototype. Eric/Jiten/Thomas to come up with a technical road map for the BioCatalogue project
 5. Katy is doing a (taverna) poster for the ISMB meeting. Biocatalogue will be mentioned on this poster

On Round table

Thomas worked with Hamish on the installation of rails and apache+mongrel cluster at EBI.

Eric worked on extending the db model and understanding how rails handles db models. Concern was raised about db integrity in the absence of rails. Another concern was that rails handling of RDF is inadequate

Jiten and Katy have been busy preparing for the ISMB Meeting

There is a student intern at Manchester that can be brought into the biocatalogue project. He could be a good candidate for doing the interfacing between myExperiment and BioCatalogue.

Carole has a few publicity opportunities for the BioCatalogue project in the following weeks(Bonn -talking to Max-Planck people, UK e-Science All Hands, SYSMO). An expanded webpage will be needed to make these publicity opportunities more effective. Thomas and Rodrigo agreed to add content to the BioCatalogue holding page

On Other Business

A developer blog for BioCatalogue is something that will not be done at the moment. But the issue can be revisited in the future

Rodrigo will follow up the issue of giving access to the Manchester people on the EBI ticket tracking system

Robert wanted assistance in writing some workflows. Robert also raised the question of best practice in annotating a service. There was a suggestion that an example driven minimum effort to effectively annotate a service was one way to go. It could also be modeled on the minimum effort for discovery, discrimination amongst the discovered services and invocation based on the bronze/silver/gold annotation model

On publishing BioCatalogue interfaces, there was a suggestion on having BioCatalogue as a service within BioCatalogue.

On wiki, there a suggestion from EBI on moving to a platform with BioCatalogue look, feel and control. Given that there is a dedicated team of people handling web issues at EBI who could set up a wiki very quickly, it was agreed that EBI should setup a biocatalogue wiki and circulate the link within the next few days.

Action Items

Action Carole → Resend paper to mailing list

Action Eric → Send db schema to mailing list

Action Eric/Thoman → Investigate Passenger and Ruby Enterprise Edition for BioCatalogue pilot

Action Eric/Jiten/Thomas → Come up with a technical road map for the BioCatalogue project

Action Rodrigo → Provide access to the EBI ticketing system to BioCatalogue team in Manchester

Action Nobody → Assist in developing some workflows for Robert

Action Thomas → Setup BioCatalogue wiki and circulate link on the mailing list

Action Rodrigo & Thomas → Provide content for the BioCatalogue home page

Previous/Next Minutes

Previous meeting: PhoneMeeting_13_06_2008 

Next meeting: PhoneMeeting_10_07_2008

F2F Hackathon/Designathon 21-22-23 January @ Manchester

Attending

Thomas, Eric, Jits

Drifting in and out: Franck, Steve, Carole

Agenda

Annotations

Service testing infrastructure (based on EMBRACE capabilities)

Automated testing and continuous integration of codebase

EMBRACE + discussions with Steve

Soaplab server submission

UI

Service submission page

BioMoby support

Updating the public wiki

Ownership/provider management

DAS

Search/Browse/Filtering

Notes

Annotations

What happened to the different types of annotation? (operational, etc)

→ we need to revisit this and figure out a way of being able to display this in the UI in an effective way (possibly using icons or labels to show what kind of annotation is being shown/added).

What happened to the different levels of annotation? (platinum, etc)

→ discussed this with Steve: why do users care about the different levels of annotations?? Is it only for service providers? Is it possible to make the levels of colours meaningful to users?? We need to make it clear that this is not necessarily an indication of usefulness. It's more a badge / certification thing.

→ It could be just another “badge” on services.

How to handle duplicate annotations?

→ facility in the plugin to specify which attribute names (or all) must be checked for duplication.

Idea: “One stop annotation form”:

Used in post submit (see service submission page notes) as well as anytime someone wants to add many annotations.

Provides a comprehensive number of fields to fill in, categorised into the different types of annotations (operational, etc)

Shows the level of annotation currently on the service and highlights what fields need to be filled in to achieve the different levels.

Feedback from Franck:

Very good

Can't edit own annotations when mistakes have been made!

→ we've had a very long discussion about immutability and the bottom line is that the whole curation pipeline (with curation assertions) might be nice and clever and useful for the future, but for now the urgent requirements of being able to edit and add to annotations needs to be met. Ie: make annotations editable (but store last edited versions).

→ simple way of editing an annotation - clever stuff later.

The annotation popup UI (with dark background) thing is not the best for usability. Can't copy/paste or check other annotations.

→ possibly have inline adds/edits (users can then copy/paste). Steve: need to make it more lightweight and inline, with button to go into modal mode if required.

→ we discussed whether it should have an active save or close/cancel button or both.

Need the ability to add name aliases for operations/input/outputs.

Need to fix: after annotation, tab changes back to default one.

Fix centering bug for modal window.

Automated testing and continuous integration of codebase

Need automated tests for at least the models in the codebase as well as more coverage for newer functionality. Candidates tools:

Rspec (more behavioural - higher learning curve)

Runit (more standard unit testing) ← we will stick to this.

Need continuous integration. Candidate server tools:

Cerberus

Cruise

Hudson

CruiseControl.rb

Need server to run it on (could do at EBI).

Policy agreed:

write basic unit tests for existing models.

write tests for any new features from now on. Especially new models.

set up and maintain a continuous integration server (Feb 09).

Soaplab server submission

Franck:

“utilities bundled/packaged into just SOAP services”

“automatically generated”

“Soaplab server → Tools”

CONCLUSION - each indidvidual “tool” in a Soaplab server is just a SOAP Service + extra metadata to show it is part of grouping. I.e.: Soaplab is more a grouping structure, NOT a service type.

We need the notion of ServiceGroups - these are applicable to other things, not just Soaplab servers.

Do we need relationships? Is “part of group” just a kind of relationship? Other relationships like alternates and so on will also be required in the future.

→ Yes and yes.

Duplication checks handled in the existing SOAP manner.

Can we determine when a user is submitting a SOAP service that it is actually part of a Soaplab server?

→ we should probably have a check in case someone wants to register a service in a Soaplab server as a SOAP service (maybe check for <xsd:import namespace=“http://soaplab.org/typedws” line).

SPECIAL CASE: An issue is in the way EMBOSS names the tools - it embeds subgrouping of tooling (aka classification) within the URLs of the WSDL, and the endpoints, of each SOAP service generated. E.g.: http://www.ebi.ac.uk/soaplab/typed/services/edit.aligncopy?wsdl and http://www.ebi.ac.uk/soaplab/typed/services/edit.aligncopy … where “edit.aligncopy” means that the tool is “aligncopy” and it belongs to the “edit” subgroup (ie: category) of tools. This allows them to generate documentation like this: http://www.ebi.ac.uk/soaplab/. Also the real name of the service is extrapolated from this (using: subgroup.toolname).

→ we can translate these to classification annotations (or just plain tags) and the names can be used to replace the name in the WSDL (which often aren't very useful).

So from some Soaplab servers we can get:

Category annotations on each individual soap service

The “real name” of each individual soap service (the name in wsdl will become aliases [ie: name annotations])

Eric to research more and produce a proposed model. He will also try and figure out how to get back the list of all tools (services) within a Soaplab server in a programmatic manner.

Steve: do the subgroups thing have any meaning outside of EMBOSS?? If not, why should we treat them separately?

We could possibly register Soaplab as a service with children services. But not making exceptions, just tagging as being a Soaplab service.

Comment by Jits [2009-01-27 13:32]: just spoke to Katy and she said that what EMBOSS do (ie: category.name) is very common to all Soaplab servers, but she is happy with the way we are treating it, ie: SOAP services with extra annotations and metadata to say it is part of a group.

REST services support

Thomas and Steve are happy with the model developed by Jits and Eric.

The structure information needs to be given by the submitter (can't be extracted from a description document as we're not using WADLs). BUT we need to keep track of the fact that the submitter gave this information! As previously, all “service structure” information had to be specified only by a provider. Now it is possible (and essential actually) that users can submit information about a service's structure.

→ we need to add a “source” to all service structure models

In the UI, for now, we can allow users to add to the service structure for REST but not SOAP etc (as it doesn't make sense for services that do have a description document).

Service submission

What is generic in that process (for all service types):

Annotations:

Name alias

Description

Documentation URL

Classification (? see notes on discussion with Steve)

Related projects

Type(s) of data the service deals with

Tags

Version identifier

Cost (free or not?)

IDEA: after submission, have a generic annotations page that be used to add many annotations at once (the “one stop annotation form” - see notes on annotations above).

SO: we need to do a very quick/minimalist 1 step submission THEN provide a form to add annotations (+ links like “remind me later”, “send to someone else to fill in for me” etc).

Maybe not go for a preset of classifications, as it might be hard to get right.

Also see notes on ownership/provider management below.

Ownership/provider management

Agree to keep the notion of ServiceProviders “virtual” but have users assigned as “owners” or “maintainers” of services.

Possibly: manual approval process for owners of a service? Where user fills in a form and we approve it.

Would probably be a 2 step process:

Verify identity of the user.

Verify that they are indeed in the capacity to be the owner/maintainer of the service on BioCatalogue.

Or alternatively: Thomas: google asking to put a small file on your domain so they can verify. Is this feasible for us?

FOR NOW:

Have check box on service submission asking “Are you the owner/maintainer of this?”

Then UI show them as “unverified” owner/maintainer.

Then afterwards verify their identity and show them as “verified”.

Verification of a user's global identity on BioCatalogue could be stored (to prevent from having to ascertain their actual identity each time).

Thomas: what about “contacts”? “Can you be contacted about issues to do with this Service?”

Eric: users can select what relationship they have to a service (“user”, “maintainer”, etc)

Is this an owner of a service? or a service deployment?

→ Actually they are really the owner of a service deployment. So one service on BioCatalogue could have multiple owners.

Service testing

Steve (on EMBRACE's service testing):

Service test infrastructure separate from Drupal.

Drupal is just aware of the tables that the service test populates (ie: mysql is the common data source).

“Scheduler” (run by cron) in a separate test server runs the tests and populates the db.

Just scripts that can be populated from command line, return 0, 1, anything (latter is “something strange happened”). Any output is accumulated in a log file and stored in db to show.

Around this is a wrapper (harness executes wrapper with script as argument… tries to trap any bad behaviour. The wrapper talks to the db in terms of putting results into the db.

The wrapper/harness needs to know about users at one point - in order to inform users of a change in status (ie: emails the email submitter). Possibly use event logging + background process to do this in the future.

What we haven't done a good job of is - uploading of zips of tests + specify command to execute (ie: name of the script). Zip allows upload of extra code together with script.

What we would like to do is automatic tests…. ping? parse wsdl (is it still valid)? Suite of tests…

Additional notes:

CRON ask for tests not running currently, and run them sequentially.

Test are scripts which run from command line with no parameters returning 0,1,something else (0=ok, 1=fail, other=something strange happened).

Wrapper will talk to the db and run the scripts. If scripts segfault or go bonkers, the wrapper will be fine and know something went wrong.

Wrapper or harness need to know about users to be able to mail the person who registered the service when something goes wrong.

EBI to check if we can open Mysql access to unique host outside (Man. Uni.).

Scripts are also a good start for developing own client.

Scripts are uploaded as zip with script or whatever is needed for the script to run + command to run.

EMBRACE + discussions with Steve

cache wsdl 1st time uploaded to check if it changed. If changed, then put the service in amber and mail the provider/owner and give them a link asking them to verify any changes. “We've noticed people modifying the wsdl and not updating the docs.” This has helped catch out some service changes.

validate wsdl

ping service

WSI compliant test script (already done & working in EMBRACE registry)

DAS document validator

tag suggestion very important

maybe SOAPLAB should just be shown as a tag

we need a generic relationship mechanism (“I'm part of a group…”, “I'm similar/identical to…”, “I'm an alternative version to…”, “I'm related to…”)

nice to have 2 types of tests: from owner and from users (possibility to promote user tests by owner)

annotations: could use revisions instead of editing but making looks like it's a simple edit (doing revision in the background)

public part of the wiki should be dumped on to the website as static pages

OR try to make the wiki look like the website

basic filtering is needed (provider/type/tags)

metallic code is for provider, not for user (capture quality of annotation)

traffic light capture reliability

star rating capture usefullness/quality/value ?

can we really do classification services? Classification only works only if we know the classifications beforehand. Can we not just use tags?

we need to find some biologists and ask them how they find services.

UI

bottom links don't stay at the bottom when click on tabs in IE (content not pushing )

next step for me would be to finish off the user “area” (password, profile…)

check in the annotation icon relocation

move side boxes inside body content & stop using sidebar layout for now

for annotations, we'll provide a Save and Cancel buttons → active saving for annotations

Search/Browse/Filtering

Browse: Need to be able to dynamically harvest the tags from subset to present them as categories/cloud

Meeting Agenda/Minutes

Date: Tuesday 07th October 2008

Time: 15:00-17:00 (UK)

Attending

Manchester: Franck, Jits,

EBI: Eric, Thomas

Apologies

Carole, Hamish, Rodrigo

Minuting

Jits

Agenda

Action from the last telcon.

Progress with the pilot - are we rolling?

AOB.

Actions from Previous Meeting

Franck: Gather requirement for the pilot… DONE during the EBI “designathon” (see: requirements_for_pilot)

Jits: Speak to Dave about the new privacy policy in myExperiment… ONGOING

Everyone: read EBI privacy policy… DONE

Franck: contact Eddie from BioMoby for help in registring BioMoby services…. DONE, Eddie has provided a script we could potentially use.

Minutes

Discussed how BioMoby services fit in. There are some complications here that need to be tackled once we have the basic SOAP service submission fully working. This brought up the idea of “service groupings”, so people can see a list of all “BioMoby” services, for example.

Agreed that we need to start deploying the pilot code somewhere so that we can show internal people, as well as get Franck to start populating the pilot content database. Eric and Thomas volunteered to be responsible for this (together with Hamish's help).

Franck brought up and reminded us about the requirement for bulk submission of services. This is crucial to getting content in the pilot.

We also discussed tagging and how it may fit in with the annotation model being developed. To users, though, we figured that they would be visualised differently to regular annotations.

New Actions

Franck (with devs): put together feature list for pilot, for end users.

Jits: circulate myExp draft T&C's and privacy policy.

Eric & Thomas: set up pilot.biocatalogue.org and deploy the current work on the pilot.

Next Meeting

Tues 14/10/2008

Upcoming Meetings

AOB

Previous/Next Meetings

Previous meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Sept 30 2008

Next meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Oct 14 2008

Mass Curator: Developer Information

The Mass Curator tool is developed using JRuby[1] (v 1.5.1) and is licenced under GPL 3.

This project utilizes BioCatalogue's read API to GET all the services, and the write API to POST the annotations data.

IMPORTANT

The project was only put into testing under the Mac OS X platform (10.5). Testing on other platforms is required.

Only Excel 97-2004 workbooks (.xls) are currently supported.

Building Mass Curator

The source code for this project is hosted on GitHub at http://github.com/myGrid/BioCatalogue-Mass-Curator

To build the project locally, checkout a copy of the the source code from the repository by running git clone git://github.com/myGrid/BioCatalogue-Mass-Curator.git

The packaging for this tool is handled by the JRuby gem - RAWR[2]. To install this, run sudo jruby -S gem install rawr

Mass Curator is dependant on the following libraries (all of which are included in the source's lib folder as JAR archives).

BrowserLauncher [3] (Java library)

spreadsheet [4] (JRuby gem)

parseconfig [5] (JRuby gem)

libxml-jruby [6] (JRuby gem)

json-jruby [7] (JRuby gem)

The application's configuration is done via a mass-curator.conf file. This needs to be placed in the directory you wish to run the application from. If no mass-curator.conf file is found, the default settings will be used, but they will not be saved. To use the default settings and allow for the preferences to be saved, place an empty mass-curator.conf file in the application's directory. You can also specify your own settings by placing something like this into the file: [8]

[application]
biocatalogue-hostname = "http://sandbox.biocatalogue.org"
services-per-page = 15
search-results-per-page = 10

[spreadsheet]
include-help = false

If you wish to run the application using the uncompiled source, run the command ./run-dev.sh from your working directory.

To build an executable JAR archive, run rake rawr:jar from your working directory. Make sure you are using the JRuby version of rake, otherwise the build will fail. There is no need to run rawr install as the configuration files come as part of the source.

To execute the created JAR from the top level working directory, run java -jar package/jar/BioCatalogue-Mass-Curator.jar

For a complete list of commands, run rake -T

Project Format

The code for the project is structured in the following manner:

project root

lib (contains all the Java libraries and gems required in JARs)

resources (contains all the images and other data resources)

package (where all the builds go by default, this is exempt from source control)

src (contains the actual code to drive the application)

events (where event handlers and action listeners live)

models (the data models used by the application such as Service)

modules (common code used by the application, e.g error handling and logging, error/information dialogs, etc)

org (the is where the RAWR autogenerated application launcher file lives)

ui (all of the user interface components i.e. panels and windows)

Apart for the run-dev.sh script, the Licence, and the ReadMe.rdoc file, the top level of the project root contains 2 other files of interest: build_configuration.rb and Rakefile. These 2 files are used by RAWR, together with src/org/rubyforge/rawr/Main.rb to drive the builds and execution of the compiled binaries.

The top level of the src directory contains 3 important files: main.rb, application_requires.rb and application_constants.rb; main.rb serves as an entry point for the program, application_constants.rb declares which files and classes are needed by the application, and application_requires.rb does the actual loading of the JRuby application, libraries, and user configuration settings into memory. Mass Curator uses eager loading for Java classes. Lazy loading the Java classes increases the startup time by only a fraction of a second; loading of all classes before hand, allows for slightly cleaner and manageable code. As far as application events go, loading is done as needed.

Logging facilities are provided by the logger from Ruby's core library, writing to mass-curator.log which appears in the same directory as the running instance. For development purposes, the log's output can be redirected to the standard output (console) by providing the executable with the argument –log-to-stdout before launch (see run-dev.sh).

Data Model and Relationships

Mass Curator's data model consists of 3 objects: Service, ServiceComponent, and ServiceComponentIO. Service is analogous to the Service model in the BioCatalogue. Each Service has a collection of ServiceComponents in the form of a hash mapping id ⇒ ServiceComponent. A ServiceComponent is analogous to a BioCatalogue SOAP operation and a REST endpoint[9]. A ServiceComponent contains hashes for the “inputs” and “outputs”, both mapping id to ServiceComponentIO. ServiceComponentIO is anagolous to SOAP inputs, SOAP outputs, and REST input parameters[10] in the BioCatalogue.

Services are only created as needed, and likewise for ServiceComponents and ServiceComponentIOs. When an API call is made to the BioCatalogue to retrieve some services, only the Service object is instantiated. The Service model has a fetchComponents method, which will instantiate and build the relationships between the objects in the data model tree. Each model tree contains a list of descriptions; this list is also populated when fetchComponents is called.

Caching

Services are cached, and the cache is frequently updated to contain all the information available about that service; if Service#fetchComponents is called, the cached Service will contain all the descriptions and the relationships, otherwise it will just be the Service entry with the basic information. The instance method fetchComponents is usually called when exporting Services to a spreadsheet. Caches have been implemented for the service browser and the current search results; a cache for all searches made may be required.

[1] http://jruby.org

[2] http://rawr.rubyforge.org

[3] http://browserlaunch2.sourceforge.net

[4] http://spreadsheet.rubyforge.org

[5] http://rubyforge.org/projects/parseconfig

[6] http://github.com/dylanvaughn/libxml-jruby

[7] http://json-jruby.rubyforge.org

[8] A full list of configuration options will be made available soon

[9] , [10] not currently implemented

This page is now deprecated. Please do not update!

Web Services change their location and capability, or become outdated

The BioCatalogue monitors Web Services and records historical data on the availability, reliability and functionality of these services

Monitoring of Web Services in the BioCatalogue

The BioCatalogue regularly monitor services to provide up-to-date information about the status of the service. The catalogue regularly pings the endpoint and the WSDL of the Web Service. The results of the monitoring provide information about the availability and reliability of the service and are shown as traffic light in the BioCatalogue.

Green (put icon): The service is available, its WSDL and endpoint can be accessed

Amber (put icon): The service might not be available, its WSDL or its endpoint or both are not accessible.

Red (put icon): The service is not accessible.

When you first register a service it will be marked blue (icon here) until the automated monitoring check its status.

The result of the monitoring for the past 4 days are shown.